Mss.B.H334
American Philosophical Society
Isaac and I. Minis Hays papers
Circa 1820-1925
Mss.B.H334
American Philosophical Society
1.75 Linear feet Ca. 1000 items; 4 upright boxes, 1 volume
These papers reflect Isaac Hays' interests and activities in the medical profession and as an editor. His interest in paleontology, especially in the controversy with G. W. Featherstonhaugh, is also represented. There is one separate volume (77 letters) containing correspondence about natural history and naturalists, written to Hays by C. L. Bonaparte, George Ord, Thomas Say, and Charles A. Lesueur. The correspondence in the larger collection, however, contains much material on the American Journal of the Medical Sciences, particularly illuminated in the correspondence with John D. Godman. The I. Minis Hays material consists of letters from doctors, relating to medicine and medical publications and editing, as well as medical organizations. Most significant of the correspondence is that with John Shaw Billings (ca. 60 letters).
Ca. 1250 items.
Hays, I. Minis, (Isaac Minis), 1847-1925
Hays, Isaac,1796-1879.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Part of this collection is also available on microfilm (Film 1363).
Biographical/Historical note
Isaac Hays (1796-1879, APS 1863) was an ophthamologist and medical publications editor. He was a surgeon at Will's Ophthalmic Hospital in Philadelphia (1834-1854) and was one of the first to study colorblindness and astigmatism.
Isaac Minis Hays (1847-1925, APS 1886 ) was a Philadelphia physician, ophthalmologist, editor and librarian. He was the editor of the American Journal of the Medical Sciences from 1878-1890. He later became Secretary and Librarian of the American Philosophical Society from 1897-1922. As A.P.S. Librarian, he collected and cataloged the great mass of Benjamin Franklin’s papers for the American Philosophical Society. He also published a Calendar of Franklin Papers (1907) and a C[h]ronology of Benjamin Franklin (2nd ed., 1913).
Hays was born in Philadelphia on July 26, 1847, the son of Dr. Isaac Hays (1796-1879, APS 1863) and Sarah Minis. He was sent to the Classical Institute for his secondary education, and afterward matriculated at the University of Pennsylvania. He graduated A.B. in 1866 and immediately entered Penn’s medical school, graduating M.D. in 1868. Remaining an extra year, he took a Master of Arts degree in 1869. Also, in 1869 he became the assistant editor to his father Isaac Hays, who was the editor of the American Journal of Medical Sciences.
Hays wrote or edited several works in his field of ophthalmology, including the American edition of J. Soelberg Wells’s Treatise on the Diseases of the Eye (1873) and a statistical survey, entitled “Blindness: Its Frequency, Causes and Prevention” for William F. Norris and Charles A. Oliver’s System of Diseases of the Eye (1897). However, Hays took little pleasure in the practice of medicine (having few patients) or in medical research.
Hays succeeded his father as editor of the American Journal of Medical Sciences, after his father’s death in 1878. Already as assistant editor, he had commissioned four historical articles to demonstrate American contributions over the previous century to Medicine, Surgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology. These appeared in successive quarterly issues of the Journal in 1876, and were reprinted as a monograph entitled, A Century of American Medicine. Several years after becoming editor, Hays converted a sister publication of the Journal, the monthly Medical News and Library, to a weekly format. He conceived the publication, containing extracts from other journals, as a “medium” for “transmitting the earliest intelligence of medical discoveries and progress,” and recruited special correspondents in other cities for this purpose. These endeavors gave Hays a notable reputation as a medical editor.
Hays’s earliest experiences with libraries came after his election as a Fellow of the College of Physicians of Philadelphia in 1872. The following year he was appointed to the Library Committee of the College, and pursued its work with creativity and energy. One of his greatest concerns was to see that the College library was properly cataloged, and he visited the Library Company of Philadelphia and the Boston Medical Library to learn about the costs, materials and systems for cataloging the collection. He even concerned himself with the particulars of the library’s operations, designing charge slips, helping to draft rules for the use of the library, drafting a new, expanded schedule for its hours of operation, binding library and archival materials and hiring its first professional staff. As the College Librarian became more experienced in his post, the need for the Library Committee to be involved in the day-to-day operations lessened. Hays was displeased by this “restriction” in the Committee’s authority, and offered his resignation in 1893.
Hays’ earlier editorial and library committee assignments would be excellent preparation for his work at the American Philosophical Society. He was elected to membership in the Society in February of 1886, and eleven years later became one of its secretaries. He was also appointed acting librarian to replace of Dr. George H. Horn (1840-1897, APS 1869), who had fallen ill. Within a few weeks of his new appointments he began initiatives for changes that would occupy the Society for a quarter of a century. Serving as the A.P.S. Librarian, secretary and editor, Hays was effectively its first executive officer. During the twenty-five year period from 1897-1922 he is said to have written 48,000 letters on Society business and edited twenty-seven volumes of the Proceedings and Transactions. With a passion for order, a keen analytical sense, and abundant physical energy, he became the driving force behind all of the Society’s work.
Drawing upon his experiences on the Library Committee of the College of Physicians, Hays brought needed changes to the Society’s Library. On his appointment as Acting Librarian, he was invited to sit on the Library Committee and began making important recommendations. Later, after the death of the former Librarian Dr. Horn in 1898, Hays became an ex offico member of the Library Committee. Among his first recommendations were the establishment of rules governing the operation of the Library, the purchase of a card catalog, and the hiring of a professional cataloger. Other library staff was added over the next few years, totaling four by 1901. For a library cataloging system Hays adopted the Dewey Decimal Classification system to replace the “philosophical” classification of former A.P.S. Librarian J. Peter Lesley (1819-1903, APS 1856). Next, he turned to the Library’s neglected books and periodicals that were badly in need of binding. He identified and sold duplicate volumes and withdrew books outside the Library’s fields of interest, donating many pamphlets on Unitarian theology (garnered by the Society’s first Librarian John Vaughan (1756-1841, APS 1784)) to the First Unitarian Church. Hays extended the hours during which the Library was open to readers, and also asked for increased space. One of his most impressive accomplishments was a fifteen-year project to bind and catalog the papers of Benjamin Franklin. Having proceeded with the organization of the Library, Hays now turned to the A.P.S. Committee on Historical Manuscripts for advice about how to make the Society’s many large collections accessible to researchers. On the Committee’s recommendation calendars were prepared for the papers of Richard Henry Lee, Nathanael Greene and General George Weedon. Hays is best known outside the Society for promoting the Benjamin Franklin papers, donated to the Society by Charles Pemberton Fox in 1840. This collection was little known or used for much of the nineteenth-century, although Paul L. Ford used it extensively for his 1899 portrait, The Many-Sided Franklin. Shortly after Hays’ appointment as Librarian, A.P.S. member Talcott Williams (1849-1928, APS 1888) suggested to him that a calendar be prepared for the Franklin papers. Hays presented the idea of a Franklin Collection calendar to the A.P.S. Council along with a proposal that the Society celebrate the bicentennial of Franklin’s birth in 1906. Neither proposal was adopted. Consequently, he changed his tactics. In the final paper of a scientific session at the General Meeting that year, the Chairman of the Library Committee Joseph G. Rosengarten ( 1835-1921, APS 1891) described the content and character of the Franklin papers, expressing the hope that a calendar might be prepared for the collection in the not too distant future—“certainly by the two hundredth anniversary of the birth of our founder.” In the business meeting that followed Hays gained unanimous consent for a committee “to prepare a plan for the appropriate celebration of the bicentennial of the birth of Franklin.”
The plans for a bicentennial celebration of Franklin’s birth drew widespread support, from the U.S. government, the Pennsylvania legislature, and the city of Philadelphia. On April 20, 1906 dignitaries from across the nation and the globe assembled in Philadelphia to celebrate the bicentennial. These included Senator Henry Cabot Lodge, leading the congressional delegation; Ambassador Jean A.A. J. Jusserand (1855-1932, APS 1907), representing the French Republic; as well as delegates from 127 learned societies. In addition to addresses on Franklin by leading scholars, there were luncheons, dinners and two academic convocations. There were also memorial ceremonies at Franklin’s grave. The grateful members of the Society recognized Hays achievement with an illuminated scroll and an engraved silver cup. After the departure of guests, the Committee on the Franklin Bicentennial directed Hays to prepare a memorial volume and “to secure the services of a corps of assistants to complete the Calendar of the Franklin papers.” The calendar appeared in five large volumes in 1908.
As A.P.S. Secretary Hays resuscitated the spirit of the Society just as he had revived its Library. By the last decade of the nineteenth century, attendance at the Society’s semi-monthly meetings was meager. The number of attendees rarely reached thirty. In 1901 Hays proposed that the Society hold an annual general meeting, lasting several days to attract distant members instead of the semi-monthly meetings. His plan was approved, and the first general meeting was held on April 3-5, 1902 and was a resounding success. 115 members attended, and such meetings became a regular feature of the Society’s calendar. Sometimes the general meetings were planned around an anniversary or special theme like the centennial of Darwin’s birth. In 1910 ordinary meetings were reduced to one a month, and in 1936 monthly meetings were dropped completely in favor of a second general meeting.
Hays’ other major initiative within the American Philosophical Society was less successful. The reawakening of the members’ interest in the Society and its mission naturally produced a desire for larger quarters. This was especially the case, since member attendance at general meetings had grown significantly and the library had outstripped the available space. As a matter of fact, in 1912 some books from the Library’s collection had to be put into storage at a neighboring bank. At this time in Philadelphia the new Parkway was taking shape under the leadership of former Fairmount Park Commissioner Eli Kirk Price, Jr. (1860-1933, APS 1916), who based the plans upon the model of the Champs ď Elysees in Paris. Hays was among the Society’s members, who voted to leave the Philosophical Hall facility on Independence Square and to construct a new building at 16th and Cherry streets. To this end he mounted a fund-raising campaign, playing a large part in the related meetings, discussions and publicity. However, the advent of World War I diverted the attention of the members and the public for a number of years. In 1922 before the relocation scheme could be realized, the city of Philadelphia decided to use the 16th and Cherry Street tract for a park.
In the spring of 1922 Hays shocked the members of the American Philosophical Society with an announcement of his retirement. The members were genuinely dismayed, since few active members could recall a time when he had not been in charge. After his resignation, Hays continued to be an active and outspoken A.P.S. member. Among his activities, he was appointed Chairman of the Committee on Library, and in this capacity he wrote an article on Benjamin Franklin’s Canada pamphlet entitled, The Interest of Great Britain Considered (1760), as well as answering questions from a new generation of Franklin scholars such as George Simpson Eddy. In 1924 Hays served as secretary of a special committee to plan an international scientific conference to celebrate the Society’s two hundredth anniversary in 1926. He presented his plan for the celebration on May 27, 1925. Unfortunately, he would not live to see it realized. Ten days later, the seventy-seven year old Hays died of a heart attack on June 5, during a heat wave of unseasonable intensity. In his will Hays directed that after the death of his daughters, the income of his considerable estate should be paid to the American Philosophical Society, the institution he had served for thirty-seven years.
Early American History Note
Isaac Hays was a Philadelphia ophthalmologist who was also deeply involved in natural history. The Isaac Hays material has two discreet sections: a volume of correspondence for 1824-1855 and a collection of loose manuscripts. The first part of the collection is a bound volume that contains the correspondence Hays carried on with other prominent naturalists in the nineteenth century from 1824–1855, although the bulk come from the 1820s and early 1830s. Prominent correspondents in this series include Charles Lucien Bonaparte, George Ord, Thomas Say, and Charles Lesueur. All of the correspondence is incoming, addressed to Hays. Occasionally the correspondence involves commentary on other current events in addition to the obvious scientific nature of the correspondence. A letter from Bonaparte, for instance, discusses the rivalry between the Philadelphia and New York orchestras. The Ord correspondence, written mostly from Europe, makes reference to Audubon, Ord’s ornithological rival, and scientific publications and thought prominent in Europe. The Say correspondence, written from New Harmony, also provides insight on that utopian experiment and his relationship with Lesueur, who also settled in New Harmony. There are only a few Lesueur letters, all of which are in French and written from New Harmony.
The second part of the collection is loose correspondence, which takes up two boxes, and contains exchanges from a wide array of individuals. The correspondence is a mix of notes of acknowledgements and science related exchanges. Many of the letters discuss recent publications and exchange information related to printed publications. A series of letters on the George William Featherstonehaugh controversy are of particular note. Featherstonehaugh was a U.S. geologist who, according to these letters, gave a lecture in Philadelphia in August 1831. Franklin Peale, Alexander Dallas Bache, Reuben Haines, Henry Carey, and Isaac Lea were in attendance and were shocked to hear Featherstonehaugh claim that fossil remains of a mastodon did not represent a new species, but were instead bones of a young species already discovered. Later, Isaac Hays wrote a letter to Featherstonehaugh accusing him of attacking his Hays’ “private character.” The ensuing debate is contained in this collection.
Related Archival Materials note
Biographical tributes to Caspar Wistar, 1918 - Mss.B.W76a
A note on the history of the Jefferson manuscript draught of the Declaration of Independence in the Library of the American Philosophical Society, 1898 - Mss.973.3.H33n
Testimonial to Isaac M. Hays, 1906 - Mss.B.H335a
Custodial History note
I. Minis Hays material (call number Mss.B.H334.1) originally part of Isaac Hays collection purchase. I. Minis Hays material interfiled with Mss.B.H334 in 2011.
Bache, Franklin, 1792-1864; Barton, Thomas Pennant, 1803-1869; Beck, John B., (John Brodhead), 1794-1851; Bertin, G.; Bigelow, Jacob, 1786-1879; Billings, John S., (John Shaw), 1838-1913; Bonaparte, Charles Lucian, 1803-1857; Bowditch, Henry I., (Henry Ingersoll), 1808-1892; Breck, Samuel, 1771-1862; Brigham, Amariah, 1798-1849; Brongniart, Alexandre, 1770-1847; Cabell, J. L., (James Lawrence), 1813-1889; Caldwell, Charles, 1772-1853; Coxe, John Redman, 1773-1864; Crittenden, John J., (John Jordan), 1787-1863; Dewees, William, 1768-1841; Drake, Daniel, 1785-1852; Draper, John William, 1811-1882; Featherstonhaugh, George William, 1780-1866; Fisher, John D., (John Dix), 1797-1850; Flint, Austin; Furness, Horace Howard, 1833-1912; Godman, John D., (John Davidson), 1794-1830; Gross, Samuel D., (Samuel David), 1805-1884; Hayward, George, 1791-1863; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894; Jackson, James, 1796-1870; Jacobi, A. (Abraham), 1830-1919; Jusserand, J. J., (Jean Jules), 1855-1932; Keating, William Hypolitus, 1799-1840; Lea, Henry Charles, 1825-1909; Lesueur, Charles Alexandre, 1778-1846; Lewell, Thomas; Longmore, Robert; Marsh, George Perkins, 1801-1882; Meddlemore, Richard; Nuttall, Thomas, 1786-1859; Ord, George, 1781-1866; Reed, William B., (William Bradford), 1806-1876; Say, Thomas, 1787-1834; Sewall, Thomas, 1786 or 7-1845; Smith, N. R., (Nathan Ryno), 1797-1877; Stillé, Alfred, 1813-1900; Warren, John Collins, 1778-1856; Welch, William Henry, 1850-1934; General Correspondence; Medical publishing -- United States -- 19th century.; Medical publishing -- United States.; Medicine -- Societies, etc.; Medicine -- United States -- 19th century.; Medicine -- United States.; Natural History; Natural history.; Naturalists.; Paleontology.; Physicians -- United States.; Science and Technology; Scientific Data; Social Life and Custom
- Papers, 1.75 lin. feet 4 upright boxes, 1 volume
  - Table of Contents, 1967; Mss.B.H334
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    525ms
  - Abram from I. Minis Hays, 1914 Mar. 8; Mss.B.H334.1
    1967 525ms
  - Ackinson, Ralph to I. Minis Hays, 1885 Feb. 18; Mss.B.H334.1
  - Adami, J. George to I. Minis Hays, 1899 Jul. 24; Mss.B.H334.1
    1967 562ms
  - Allen, Andrew H. to I. Minis Hays, 1898 Jul. 27; Mss.B.H334.1
  - Althaus, J. to Isaac Hays, 1878 Feb. 20; Mss.B.H334
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences to Isaac Hays, 1856 Dec. 9; Mss.B.H334
  - American Opthalomological Society to Isaac Hays, 1864 Oct. 4; Mss.B.H334
  - American Philosophical Society to I. Minis Hays, 1906 Apr. 20; Mss.B.H334.1
    Scope and Contents note
    Invitation to the Franklin Bi-Centenary.
  - American Philosophical Society Proceedings, undated; Mss.B.H334.1
  - Amussat, A. to Isaac Hays, 1868 Oct. 10; Mss.B.H334
  - Anderson, Mrs. from I. Minis Hays, 1913 Mar. 13; Mss.B.H334.1
  - Bache, Franklin to Isaac Hays, 1844 Nov. 30; Mss.B.H334
  - Barnes, William to I. Minis Hays, 1876 Dec. 12; Mss.B.H334.1
  - Bartlett, Elisha to Isaac Hays, 1838 Feb. 27; Mss.B.H334
    1967 940ms
  - Barton, Thomas Pennant to Isaac Hays, undated; Mss.B.H334
    March 18.
  - Bean, William B. to Whitfield Jenks Bell, Jr., 1975 Dec. 3; Mss.B.H334
    Hays, I. Minis, (Isaac Minis), 1847-1925
  - Beck, John B. to Isaac Hays, 1843-1848; Mss.B.H334
    1967 525ms (1843 Oct. 11, 1848 Apr. 29); 1967 940ms (1843 Oct. 24, 30)
    4 items: 1843 Oct. 11, 1843 Oct. 24, 1843 Oct. 30, 1848 Apr. 29
  - Beck, Theodore Romeyn to Isaac Hays, 1843-1844; Mss.B.H334
    3 items: 1843 Oct. 27, 1844 May 28, 1844 Oct. 21
    1967 562ms (1843 Oct. 27), 1967 525ms (1844 May 28), 1967 940ms (1844 Oct. 21)
  - Bedford, G. S. to Isaac Hays, 1847-1848; Mss.B.H334
    1967 525ms, 562ms (1847)
    3 items: 1847 Dec. 14, 1848 Feb. 4, 1848 Mar. 8
  - Bertin, G. to I. Minis Hays, 1891-1892; Mss.B.H334.1
    7 items: 1891 Jan. 14, Feb. 3, 16, 17, Mar. 23, Nov. 19, 1892 Dec. 30
  - Biddle, M. L. to Isaac Hays, 1860 Oct. 6; Mss.B.H334
  - Biddle, Thomas to Isaac Hays, undated; Mss.B.H334
  - Bigelow, Jacob to Isaac Hays, 1835-1848; Mss.B.H334
    1967 940ms (1835, 1838, 1847), 1967 525ms (1839, 1848)
    1835 Jul. 31, 1838 Sep. 9, 1839 Apr. 9, 1847 Apr. 25, 1848 Feb. 22
  - Bigsby, Dr. to Isaac Hays, undated; Mss.B.H334
  - Bigstrom, John to I. Minis Hays, 1903 Nov. 24; Mss.B.H334.1
  - Billings, John Shaw, 1879-1884; Mss.B.H334.1
    11 items: 1879 Nov. 18, 1884 May 22, 1884 Nov. 22, 1884 Dec. 8, 1884 Dec. 12, 1884 Dec. 16, 1884 Dec. 19, 1884 Dec. 20, 1884 Dec. 27, 1884 Dec. 30 (2)
  - Billings, John Shaw, 1885; Mss.B.H334,334.1
    46 items: 1885 Jan. 7, 1885 Jan. 10, 1885 Jan. 31, 1885 Feb. 9, 1885 Feb. 12, 1885 Feb. 19, 1885 Feb. 27 (2), 1885 Feb. 28, 1885 Mar. 14, 1885 Mar. 15, 1885 May 4 (2), 1885 May 8 (+ copy), 1885 May 10, 1885 May 11 (2), 1885 May 16, 1885 May 29 (3), 1885 Jun. 1 (2), 1885 Jun. 2 (2), 1885 Jun. 12, 1885 Jun. 28 (6), 1885 Jun. 30, 1885 Jul. 3 (+ copy), 1885 Jul. 5, 1885 Jul. 9, 1885 Jul. 12, 1885 Jul. 26, 1885 Aug. 3, 1885 Aug. 4, 1885 Aug. 4 (5 PM), 1885 Aug. 5, 1885 Aug. 6, 1885 Aug. 8
    1885 May 8, 10 originally filed with Shoemaker letters.
  - Billings, John Shaw, 1886-undated; Mss.B.H334.1
    3 items: 1886 Mar. 31, 1906 Feb. 23, undated
  - Blackman, George C. to Isaac Hays, undated; Mss.B.H334
    May 27.
  - Blair, Anna L. to I. Minis Hays, 1898 Nov. 2; Mss.B.H334.1
  - Blake, James to Isaac Hays, undated; Mss.B.H334
    Nov. 20.
  - Boardman, Henry A. to Isaac Hays, undated; Mss.B.H334
    May 7.
  - Boott, Francis to Isaac Hays, 1840 May 15; Mss.B.H334
  - Bonaparte, Charles Lucian to Isaac Hays, 1824-undated; Mss.B.H334b; 1.0 vol. Bound volume. (Volume 1, Reel 1363)
    Bound volume also containing correspondence from George Ord, Thomas Say, and C. A. Lesueur.
    1967 256g
  - Bonaparte, Charles Lucian to N. A. Vigors, 1826 Dec. 19; Mss.B.H334
    On same sheet as Vigors to G. B. Sowerby, 1826 Dec. 8
  - Bourneville, Dr. to Isaac Hays, 1872 Apr. 3; Mss.B.H334
    General note
    See: table of contents to 509.L56.45 (Scientists Collection)
  - Bowditch, Henry Ingersoll to Isaac Hays, 1843-1847
    1967 940ms (1843), 1967 525ms (1847)
    1843 Oct. 1, 1847 Oct. 21
  - Bradford, Mr. to Emma Bradford Hays, 1878-undated; Mss.B.H334
    Many letters are undated, various others from 1878. Also included is 1855 Jun. 3, "Father" to "My Dear Annie."
  - Bradford, Mrs. to Emma Bradford Hays, undated; Mss.B.H334
    June 16.
  - Bradford, Annie, 1857-undated; Mss.B.H334
    2 items: 1857 Oct. 7 from Anne, undated from Katie.
  - Bradford, G. S. to Isaac Hays, 1848 Apr. 19; Mss.B.H334
  - Breck, Samuel to Isaac Hays, 1848 Oct. 26; Mss.B.H334
  - Bralihford, Thomas W. to Isaac Hays, 1850 Jun. 29; Mss.B.H334
  - Brewerton, H. to Isaac Hays, 1863 Nov. 10; Mss.B.H334
  - Brigham, A. to Isaac Hays, 1835 Dec. 28; Mss.B.H334
  - Brigham, Amariah to Isaac Hays, 1837-1838; Mss.B.H334
    5 items: 1837 Feb. 28, 1837 Sep. 21, 1838 Jun. 22, 1838 Aug. 11, 1838 Sep. 11
  - Brongniart, Alexandre to Isaac Hays, 1823 Oct. 23; Mss.B.H334
  - Broussais to Isaac Hays, 1827 Jul. 4; Mss.B.H334
  - Bulletin Universal des Sciences to Isaac Hays, 1829 Apr. 14; Mss.B.H334
  - Cabell, J. L. to Isaac Hays, 1841 Jul. 4; Mss.B.H334
  - Caldwell, Charles, 1833 Aug. 29; Mss.B.H334
  - Calling cards, undated; Mss.B.H334.1
    10 items.
  - Carey, Samuel T. to Isaac Hays, 1833 Oct. 28; Mss.B.H334
  - Carey & Lea. Advertisement, undated; Mss.B.H334
  - Carr, Benjamin to Isaac Hays, 1828; Mss.B.H334
    3 items: July 5, Monday evening, Friday night.
  - Chapman, Nathaniel to Isaac Hays, undated; Mss.B.H334
  - Charlton, Robert M. to Isaac Hays, undated; Mss.B.H334
    Tuesday.